对于二维情况，我们考虑两个坐标框架，即原始框架A和
For the two dimensional case we consider two coordinate frames, the original frame A, and
旋转版本，坐标框架B.并且B沿正方向旋转
a rotated version of that, coordinate frame B. And B is rotated in the positive direction
通过相对于框架A的角度θ，我们描述了新的坐标框架轴
by angle theta with respect to frame A. We then described the new coordinate frame axes
就旧坐标框架轴而言，我们能够编写这些关系。
in terms of the old coordinate frame axes, and we were able to write these relationships.
然后我们以矩阵形式写了这个，最后我们得到了一个允许我们改造的公式
We then wrote this in matrix form and we ended up with a formulation that allowed us to transform
从新帧到旧帧A的向量。此旋转矩阵的列是
vectors from the new frame to the old frame A. The columns of this rotation matrix are
新的X轴是B轴，用A坐标框架表示
the new X-axis that is the B-axis expressed in terms of the A coordinate frame and the
按照A坐标框架的BY轴。
BY-axis in terms of the A coordinate frame.
我们使用了一些相当复杂的几何图形和图表来展示这一点。
We used some quite complex geometry and diagrams in order to show this.
对于三维，做这种几何结构有点复杂
For three dimensions it's a little complex to do that kind of geometric construction
所以我们将从上次采取这个重要原则。
so we're just going to take the big principle from last time.
我们将以类似的方式开始，这里是坐标框架A，我们已经提到了一个观点
We'll start off in a similar fashion, here's coordinate frame A and we've drawn a point
我们可以用关于坐标框架A的向量来描述。我是
which we can describe in terms of a vector with respect to coordinate frame A. I’m
将引入相对于坐标旋转的新坐标系B.
going to introduce a new coordinate frame B which is rotated with respect to coordinate
我们将用另一个向量定义点，矢量BP就是
frame A. And we're going to define the point with another vector, vector BP which is the
关于旋转框架B的点
point in respect to a rotated frame B.
我们将采用与二维情况相同的技巧。
We're going to pull the same trick as we did for the 2-dimensional case.
我们将把坐标系B的轴描述为以术语表示的单位向量
We're going to describe the axes of coordinate frame B as unit vectors expressed in terms
坐标框架A，它们是新旋转矩阵的列。
of coordinate frame A and they are the columns of a new rotation matrix.
在这种情况下，它是一个3x3旋转矩阵。
In this case it's a 3x3 rotation matrix.
所以我们不会经历详细的几何构造，我们将推断
So we're not going to go through the detailed geometric construction, we're going to extrapolate
从二维案例中直接写出这个表达式。
from the 2-dimensional case and just write this expression directly.
这个新的旋转矩阵将矢量从新的坐标系B变换为旧的
This new rotation matrix transforms vectors from the new coordinate frame B to the old
坐标框架A.这个三维旋转矩阵，这个3x3矩阵，有很多
coordinate frame A. This 3-dimensional rotation matrix, this 3x3 matrix, has got a lot of
类似的属性，它是2x2对应物。
similar properties to it's 2x2 counterpart.
它是正交的，有时称为标准正交矩阵。
It is an orthogonal, sometimes called orthonormal, matrix.
这意味着矩阵中的每列都是单位长度矢量。
That means each column in the matrix is a unit length vector.
矩阵中的每一列都与所有其他列正交，这意味着我可以使用
Each column in the matrix is orthogonal to all the other columns so that means if I take
第1列和第2列之间的点积等于0，第1列也相同
the dot product between column 1 and column 2 it will be equal to 0, same for column 1
和第3栏，第2栏和第3栏。
and column 3, column 2 and column 3.
这个矩阵的倒数与它的转置相同，这是非常有用的
The inverse of this matrix is the same as it's transpose and this is a really useful
属性，因为我们经常计算姿势表达式时，我们需要找到逆
property because often times when we're computing pose expressions we need to find the inverse
旋转矩阵的计算和计算转置要简单得多
of the rotation matrix and computationally it's much simpler to compute the transpose
而不是计算3x3矩阵的逆。
than it is to compute the inverse for a 3x3 matrix.
该矩阵的行列式是+1，这意味着当我们将一个向量乘以该矩阵时，
The determinant of this matrix is +1, that means when we multiply a vector by this matrix,
它的长度不变。
its length will be unchanged.
数学家会说像这样的矩阵属于特殊的正交群
A Mathematician would say that a matrix like this belongs to the special orthogonal group
尺寸为3，并且将被写为R是集合SO（3）的元素。
of dimension 3 and that'll be written as R being an element of the set SO(3).
三表示矩阵是3x3，它是在三维空间中旋转。
Three indicating that the matrix is 3x3, it is rotation in 3-dimensional space.
我们可以写下一些非常有用的旋转矩阵，我们参考这些
There are some very useful rotation matrices that we can write down, we refer to these
作为基本旋转矩阵。
as elementary rotation matrices.
然后第一个是围绕X轴的θ旋转，由θ围绕旋转
The first one then is the rotation by theta around the X axis, rotation by theta around
Y轴，最后绕θ绕Z轴旋转。
the Y axis and finally rotation by theta about the Z axis.
我们可以将它们以各种组合相乘，以实现更多目标
And we can multiply these together in various combinations in order to achieve much more
复杂的旋转;不久之后。
complicated rotations; more about that shortly.
在我们考虑二维旋转的最后一节中，我们写了一个旋转矩阵
In the last lecture when we considered 2-dimensional rotations we wrote a rotation matrix that
看起来像这样。
looks like this.
实际上，这与基本旋转矩阵的左上角相同
In fact this is identical to the top left corner of the elementary rotation matrix for
旋转绕Z.
rotation about Z.
这个的原因很直观。
The reason about this quite intuitive.
在二维情况下，我们实际上围绕看不见的Z轴旋转
In the 2 dimensional case we are actually rotating around the unseen Z axis which was
在屏幕上向我们伸出手，实际上是看不见的。
sticking up at us out of the screen and was effectively invisible.
因此，二维旋转和三维旋转之间存在等价关系
So there is an equivalence between 2-dimensional rotation and the 3-dimensional rotation around
Z轴。
the Z axis.
当我们谈论方向时，我们会根据基本序列来考虑它们
When we're talking about orientation we consider them in terms of a sequence of elementary
旋转，让我们看一下围绕X轴的旋转。
rotations, so let's look at rotations around the X-axis.
现在这是正旋转方向，所以如果我将此坐标系旋转90°
Now this was the positive rotation direction so if I rotate this coordinate frame by 90
围绕X轴的度数看起来像这样。
degrees around the X-axis it's going to look like this.
如果我围绕X轴旋转负90度，它将看起来像这样。
If I rotate it by minus 90 degrees around the X-axis it's going to look like this.
我可以围绕Y轴旋转正90度，这样就可以旋转
I can rotate it by positive 90 degrees around the Y-axis so that's a rotation that way so
正90度旋转看起来像这样，负90度旋转
positive 90 degrees rotation looks like this and a negative 90 degrees rotation is going
看起来像这样。
to look like this.
现在围绕Z轴的正向旋转是这样的，所以如果我将这个框架旋转90度
Now positive rotation around the Z-axis is this way, so if I rotate this frame 90 degrees
在Z轴周围，它看起来像是这样，或者如果我将它旋转零下90度
around the Z-axis it's going to look like this or if I rotate it by minus 90 degrees
在Z轴周围，它看起来像这样。
this.
我们来看看MATLAB中的一些基本变换矩阵。
Let's have a look at some of these elementary transformation matrices in MATLAB.
我们可以使用函数rotx创建一个围绕X轴的旋转，我将要求
We can use the function rotx to create a rotation about the X-axis and I'm going to ask for
旋转0.2
a rotation of 0.2
弧度，这就是旋转矩阵的样子。
radians and this is what the rotation matrix looks like.
我也可以用度数来指定角度，所以在这种情况下我寻找的是什么
I could have also specified the angle in terms of degrees so in this case what I look for
是围绕X轴旋转30度。
is a rotation of 30 degrees around the X-axis.
让我把那个矩阵放到一个变量中，我将它称为R，它是一个3x3
Let me put that matrix into a variable which I'm going to call R for rotation it's a 3x3
正交旋转矩阵，我们将只测试我们提到的一些属性
orthogonal rotation matrix and we'll just test some of the properties we've mentioned
早期关于正交旋转矩阵。
earlier about orthogonal rotation matrices.
我可以看一下矩阵的行列式，我们可以看到它等于1。
I can look at the determinant of the matrix and we can see that it is equal to 1.
我可以计算该矩阵的逆矩阵，我们可以看到它与它完全相同
I can compute the inverse of that matrix and we can see that it is exactly the same as
该矩阵的转置。
a transpose of that matrix.
并且在计算上这是特别方便的，而不是必须反转矩阵
And computationally this is particularly convenient instead of having to invert the matrix I can
简单地转置它。
simply transpose it.
计算上更便宜，便宜得多。
Computationally much, much cheaper.
我还可以计算一个不同轴的旋转，我可以要求围绕它旋转
I can also compute a rotation about a different axis I could ask for a rotation around the
Y轴乘以0.2
Y-axis by 0.2
弧度或围绕Z轴的旋转，再次为0.3
radians or a rotation around the Z-axis, again by 0.3
弧度。
radians.
工具箱还包含一个功能，允许我以图形方式描绘其中一个旋转
The toolbox also contains a function which allows me to graphically depict one of these rotation
矩阵作为旋转坐标系。
matrices as a rotated coordinate frame.
所以我可以将自动变量ans中的最后一个结果传递给函数
So I can pass the last result, which is in the automatic variable ans into the function
trplot和这里我们可以看到旋转坐标系的表示。
trplot and here we can see the representation of the rotated coordinate frame.
此处指示参考坐标系，并显示旋转的坐标系
The reference coordinate frame is indicated here and the rotated coordinate frame is shown
这里是蓝色的。
here in blue.
trplot函数有很多很多选项。
The trplot function has got many, many options.
我们可以改变坐标框架的颜色，我们可以在框架上添加标签
We can change the color of the coordinate frame, we can add a label to the frame, we
可以添加箭头等。
can add arrowheads and so on.